Preliminary Guide to the Richard A. Preston Papers, circa 1745 - 1987 (bulk 1956-1987) UA.29.02.0065
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Richard A. Preston papers
circa 1745-1987 (bulk 1956-1987)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Preston, Richard Arthur
UA.29.02.0065
36 Linear Feet
Richard Arthur Preston (b. 1910), a leading British Commonwealth scholar, was appointed the William K. Boyd Professor of History at Duke University in 1965. Major subjects of the collection include Canadian history, especially military history; the Department of History; and the Canadian Studies program at Duke. Materials include correspondence, reports, course syllabi, printed matter, manuscripts, clippings, photographs, and other papers. English.
36000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
Portions of these materials are restricted by donor request.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Richard A. Preston Papers was received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1980 (A80-225), 1981 (A81-60), 1983 (A83-96), 1985 (A85-65), and 1988 (A88-0048).
Biographical Note
Born in 1910, in Middlesbrough, England, Preston was educated at the University of Leeds (B.A., 1931; M.A., 1932; diploma in education, 1933) and Yale University (Ph.D, 1936). Preston was appointed lecturer at the University of Toronto (1936); Assistant Lecturer at the University College, Cardiff (1938-1940); a member of the Royal Air Force (1940-1945), Assistant Professor at the University of Toronto (1945), Professor of History in the Royal Military College of Canada (1948-1965), and the William K. Boyd Professor of History at Duke University (1965-1980). Preston was the director of the Canadian Studies Program at Duke University (1973-1979).
Preston was a prolific writer of scholarly articles and books. His works include:
Gorges of Plymouth Fort: A Life of Sir Ferdinando Gorges, Captain of Plymouth Fort, Governor of New England, and Lord of the Province of Maine, University of Toronto Press, 1953
Kingston before the War of 1812, Champlain Society, 1958
Canada in World Affairs, 1959-61, Oxford University Press, 1965
Canada and the Imperial Defense: A Study of the Origins of the British Commonwealth's Defense Organization, 1867-1919, Duke University Press, 1967.
Canada's RMC: A History of the Royal Military College, University of Toronto Press, 1969, new edition, 1984
The Defence of the Undefended Border: Planning for War in North America, 1867-1939, McGill-Queen's University Press, 1977
The Squat Pyramid: Canadian Studies in the United States, Center for International Studies, Duke University, 1980
Perspectives in the History of Military Education and Professionalism, U.S. Air Force Academy, 1980
To Serve Canada: A History of the Royal Military College Since the Second World War, University of Ottawa Press (Ottawa, Canada), 1991.
Preston received a number of awards during his career. He received the Commonwealth Fund fellowship (1933-36); Nuffield summer travel award (1954); Duke University summer research scholarship (1957); City of Kingston Achievement Award (1957) for his television series and publications on the history of Kingston; Canada Council senior fellowship (1963-64); Social Science Research Council grant (1963); Canada Confederation Medal (1967); Guggenheim fellowship (1971-72); Donner Memorial Medal (1975) for promotion of Canadian studies in the United States; LL.D., Royal Military College of Canada (1977); and the Northern Telecom Gold Medal (1983) for the promotion of Canadian studies. Preston was named honorary professor of history, Royal Military College of Canada (1973).
Preston married Marjorie Ethel Fishwick in 1939, and had three children.
Collection Overview
Collection includes correspondence, reports, course syllabi, printed matter, drafts, research notes, manuscripts, lectures, photographs, clippings, maps, and other papers.
The arrangement of the collection is by accession dates. These additions follow the order given in the collection file and are not presented in chronological order.
The 1981 Additions (A81-60) include extensive correspondence, numerous drafts and published articles and reviews, photocopies of primary sources, some research notes, and administrative papers dealing with the Duke University History Dept. The chief subjects include Canadian military affairs, general military history, military education, and Canadian Studies as a historical subdiscipline. There is a folder list for this addition that is part of the collection file.
The 1980 Additions includes printed material, correspondence, studies, reports, articles, drafts, proofs, outlines, lectures, syllabi, clippings, photos, maps, and other papers. Major subjects include Canadian history, especially military history and current military and defense concerns. The first major portion of this Addition is made up of correspondence about Preston's own research and writings of other scholars. Other materials include Preston's research notes; photocopies and typed copies of historical documents; and guides to historical collections. There are also administrative files about the History Dept. at Duke, and the Canadian Studies Program. There is a small amount of material about the alumni of the Royal Military College in Canada, where Preston taught for a number of years. The second major portion of this Addition focuses on various aspects of modern Canadian defense and external security, Canada and NATO, relations with the British Commonwealth, and Canadian domestic affairs.
Related Material
Canadian Studies Center Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Commonwealth Studies Center Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
History Department Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Stevenson Canadiana.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
History -- Study and teaching (Higher); Photographs; Clippings (information artifacts); Canada -- History, Military; Canada -- Study and teaching; Canada -- History; Preston, Richard Arthur; Preston, Richard Arthur; Duke University. Department of History; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University. Department of History -- Faculty; Duke University; Canada. Canadian Army -- History
- 1981 Additions (A81-60), ca. 1745-1980
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes extensive correspondence, numerous drafts and published articles and reviews, photocopies of primary sources, some research notes, and administrative papers dealing with the Duke University History Dept. The chief subjects include Canadian military affairs, general military history, military education, and Canadian Studies as a historical subdiscipline.
  - Duke University: General Administrative, 1948-1980 (Box 1)
    Contains materials on appointments, commonwealth studies, university policies, graduate students, the History Department, letters of recommendation, the military history program at Duke, oral examinations, retirement, Shell fellowships, testimonials, the University Centers for Rational Alternatives, visitors, and grant proposals.
    There are a small number of letters in the folder entitled Testimonials that are dated before 1965 and would pre-date Preston's arrival at Duke University.
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Some material in this box is RESTRICTED. Please consult University Archives staff.
  - Organizations, 1951-1973 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence, newsletters, brochures, and printed material from historical societies and other organizations to which Preston belonged.
  - Canadian Studies, 1965-1980 (Box 3)
    Includes materials on conferences, seminars, lectures, proposals, reports, syllabi, and other printed material about the Duke Canadian Studies program and other non-Duke programs.
  - Lectures, Panels, Symposia, Seminars, and Conferences, 1960-1979 (Box 3)
    Includes printed material, speeches, correspondence, and brochures.
  - Correspondence, 1951-1980 (Box 4)
    - Non-Student Correspondence, A -- Z, 1951-1980 (Box 4)
      Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by last name.
    - Student Correspondence, 1965-1980
      Some material in these boxes is RESTRICTED: Student Records. Please consult University Archives staff.
      - A -- Dendy (Box 4)
      - Dennis -- Wright (Box 5)
    - Publications Correspondence
      Includes correspondence concerning Preston's ideas, drafts, and printed material used to write speeches and articles for publication. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by title of publication or by topic. Some folders include manuscripts.
      - 1936-1980 (Box 6)
      - 1948-1979 (Box 7-8)
  - Reviews, Enquiries, Lectures, Research Notes, and Printed Material, 1948-1980 (Box 9)
    Includes reviews by Preston or written about Preston's work (1961-1980), historical enquiries (1956-1976), lectures (1952-1979), research notes and printed material (1948-1976).
  - Primary Sources, ca. 1745-ca. 1930 (Box 10)
    Includes research notes, reports, photocopies, indices, lists, bibliographies, articles, maps, manuscripts, and correspondence (ca. 1964-1976).
  - War of 1812, 1963-1975 (Box 11)
    Preston researched the War of 1812, with the thought of writing a book on this topic for the Macmillan Wars of the United States series. Includes two boxes of notecards detailing Preston's bibliographical references, drafts, photocopies, correspondence, and contract.
  - Writings, 1937-1971 (Box 12)
    Includes drafts of papers, articles, and reviews written by Preston. Some are unpublished.
  - Military Education, 1949-1977 (Box 13)
    Includes brochures, training manuals, correspondence, research notes, reports and meeting agendas.
  - Military History, 1945-1973 (Box 14)
    Includes notes, maps, course outlines, lectures, and printed material about Gettysburg, Chancellorsville, the U.S. Civil War, the Battle of El Alamein, and other battles and aspects of military history.
  - Research Material (Box 15)
    Includes printed material, maps, photograph of the Royal Military College, correspondence, and other materials.
- 1980 Additions (A80-225), 1886-1979 (bulk 1956-1979)
  Includes printed material, correspondence, studies, reports, articles, drafts, proofs, outlines, lectures, syllabi, clippings, photos, maps, and other papers. Major subjects include Canadian history, especially military history and current military and defense concerns. The first major portion of this Addition is made up of correspondence about Preston's own research and writings of other scholars. Other materials include Preston's research notes; photocopies and typed copies of historical documents; and guides to historical collections. There are also administrative files about the History Dept. at Duke, and the Canadian Studies Program. There is a small amount of material about the alumni of the Royal Military College in Canada, where Preston taught for a number of years. The second major portion of this Addition focuses on various aspects of modern Canadian defense and external security, Canada and NATO, relations with the British Commonwealth, and Canadian domestic affairs.
  Of special interest is a file containing clippings and correspondence about an anti-American article which appeared in a Canadian newspaper.
  - Defense of the Commonwealth (Box 16)
    Includes scholarly papers, reports, correspondence, news articles, notes, and government publications.
  - Speech and Lecture Files (Box 17)
    Includes notes, manuscripts, photographs, correspondence, clippings, and reports on a wide variety of topics that concern Canadian military history, politics, nationalism, Sir Ferdinando Gorges, and others. Of special interest is a file containing clippings and correspondence about an anti-American article which appeared in a Canadian newspaper.
  - Duke University (Box 18)
    - History Department (Box 18)
      Includes notes and course syllabi for courses taught by Preston.
    - Visiting Speakers (Box 18)
      Includes information about individual speakers invited by Preston to speak on campus.
  - Workshops and Seminars (Box 18)
  - Summer Correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 18)
  - Conferences, Meeting, and Symposium Files (Box 19)
  - Printed Material and Correspondence (Box 19)
    Includes correspondence, newsletters, notes, scholarly papers, articles from the Army Quarterly and the Canadian Defense Quarterly, and copies of maps.
- 1985 Additions (A85-65)
  - Sabbatical Projects and Travels, ca. 1975-ca. 1985 (Box 20)
    Includes mostly papers on Preston's sabbatical projects and travels for a study of the teachings of Canadian history in U.S. schools. Also includes grant applications, reviews, and evaluations.
    The folder on Kessinger is RESTRICTED: Personnel records.
  - Canada and Canadian Studies, ca. 1975-1985 (Box 20)
    Includes mostly Canada-related correspondence, Canadian Studies at Duke, and Canadian Studies in the U.S. Contains one folder on the speaker, Frances Halpenny, who spoke at the 1985 Friends of the Library dinner.
  - Canadian Military, ca. 1956-ca. 1980s (Box 20)
    Includes mostly correspondence and drafts of articles concerning Canadian military history and modern defense matters.
- 1988 Additions (A88-0048)
  - Canada and Canadian Studies (Box 20)
    Includes correspondence, reprints, notes, forms, and other printed material concerning the Canadian Studies program at Duke and at other schools.
  - Duke University (Box 20)
    Includes correspondence about faculty appointments and copies of the Duke University Letters, 1981-1982, a publication issued from the Office of the President.
- 1983 Additions (A83-96)
  - Administrative Papers, 1936-1980 (Box 22)
    Includes correspondence and printed material about appointments at Duke, grant and job applications, job offers, sabbaticals, salary, and retirement.
    Some of this material is RESTRICTED. Please consult University Archives staff.
  - Canadian Studies, 1976-1983 (Box 22)
    Includes correspondence and printed matter about workshops and conferences; Duke Canadian and Quebec Studies; materials for Canadian Studies in the U.S.; the N.C. Social Studies Council; and President Carter's Commission on Foreign Language and International Studies.
  - The Squat Pyramid, 1970-1982 (Box 23)
    Contains survey materials on Canadian studies in the U.S. published as The Squat Pyramid, in 1980, by the Center for International Studies at Duke. Includes correspondence, itineraries, schedules, questionnaires, notes, and evaluations concerning visits to college campuses to survey Canadian Studies programs in the U.S., and copies of Canadian Embassy files on a Canadian Studies survey conducted in the U.S. in 1976.